the science and practice of enhancing
human performance for sport play and
life Welcome to
perform I'm Dr Andy Galpin I'm a
professor scientist and the executive
director of the human performance center
at Parker University today's episode
we're going to be talking all about how
to boost your metabolism the reason I
chose this is because of all the topics
in the entire space of human performance
this probably has the most discussion
among pop culture you see it everywhere
supplements diets magazine covers
boosting metabolism boosting metabolism
you speed up your metabolism is one of
the most popular topics yet because of
that it's also fraught with
misinformation with outright lies and so
how do you understand what's going on
I'm in preparing for this show I asked a
lot of my friends many of which have
phds in the field master's degrees
registered
dietitians I just simply ask them can
you speed up your metabolism and I never
got a straight answer nobody I talked to
confidently was able to tell me yes you
can or no you can't and so I was really
excited to do this topic and break that
down for everyone because the reality of
it is we have a lot of science here
there are some extremely clear-cut
answers about whether or not you can
even have a fast or slow metabolism the
reality is you can't your metabolic rate
and my metabolic rate are not
necessarily different but despite that
there's over a dozen different
scientifically documented ways in which
you can enhance your metabolism we have
learned very recently a lot of
information about what explains why some
people can do things like eat more
calories eat more food but yet not gain
as much weight as you that is a real
phenomenon even when all other variables
are controlled for that can happen but
that's not explained by having a faster
or slower metabolism and so these topics
and many many more are what I'm going to
get into in today's show and I know know
that when you leave the episode you will
know much more about how metabolism
Works what it really is and exactly what
to do to enhance it if you so please or
so like to do that and what the true
state of the literature says on
enhancing boosting or speeding up your
metabolism as always we're going to
tackle this problem by covering the
three eyes investigate interpret and
intervene so by investigate we'll walk
through really quickly how to get this
tested or measured if you're interested
in learning more about this what are
some of the high-end ways the most
scientifically supported all the way
down to low or moderately low cost and
all the way down to free if we can from
there I will talk about how to interpret
those data so how do you know whether
you're slow or fast or high or low or
where it should be based on your age and
sex and other other factors that are
important but we're going to spend most
of our time on the third eye which is I
will cover what we know scientifically
about what works and what doesn't work
we'll get into exactly how much it works
so what's the magnitude of effect how
much will it raise my metabolism by and
for how long after that we'll talk about
the specific details of the protocols if
you will so what to take how long what
dosage what timing and so on and so
forth in the case of say supplements or
food we'll talk about other factors
including but not limited to things like
the temperature water intake spicy foods
types of exercise sleep protocols and so
forth the reality of it is
we have a lot of different options from
the lifestyle from environmental from
food and supplementation that give you
the ability potentially to increase your
metabolic rate we're going to finish the
episode by going over what I call a
couple of case studies in which I give
some sample combinations of these
factors that I have used and do use in
the folks I work with to effectively
enhance metabolic speed in a long-term
successful adherent fashion so things
that are going to be not just giving us
a short bump a shortterm effect but
something that is long lasting and
sustainable over time so to get us
started the first thing we have to talk
about is what we're even talking about
these terms as I open up the show with
are malign they're confusing and that's
in large part and often is the case just
because of simple miscommunication I'm
going to keep it brief I know in the
past and I love to talk at length about
the physiology and what's happening at
the level not going to do much of that
today but I do need to explain the
different parts because as you'll see
the episode unfold we're going to talk
about how each intervention or protocol
or thing that you can do influences each
area of metabolism and it's really
important that you do something that
covers all four of the major areas so
that you have the most likelihood of
improvement so we have to know what
those areas are and then roughly what
they mean I promise so I will keep it
very brief and by that I mean it's
Galpin Style
but it will still be brief for me now
some of you might be thinking here I'm
not incredibly interested in Fat Loss or
metabolism maybe you're already lean and
you're lean no matter what or you don't
work in the area or with clients who
care that much about fat loss so you
might be thinking to yourself this
episode isn't for me I'm just going to
sort of tune out I'm going to try to
caution you against that for a couple of
reasons one you're going to care about
your long-term metabolic health and this
is highly tied to that
and so whether just because of the fact
that you're lean now doesn't mean you
always will be lean in addition if you
do want to continue to stay lean you
need to keep this engine revved up as
high as possible for as long as possible
and so we're going to cover exactly how
to do that from what we know
scientifically in today's discussion the
second thing is what I call the higher
Delta so let's imagine a scenario in
which you consume and burn exactly 2,000
calories per day so your net equal
and at that you keep the exact same
level of muscle and energy and recovery
and performance and body fat and so on
and so forth if I could do that exact
same thing at 4,000
calories now I've got much more options
what I mean by that is if I can keep you
with the exact same for all those
variables at Double the caloric load
I've got a greater ability to increase
my food intake which means my
micronutrients go up if I eat double the
food I get double the vitamins and
minerals and nutrients and fiber intake
and if I'm staying at the exact same
body composition body mass that is a
huge Advantage additionally it now
becomes far easier to lose weight if you
ever want to do that one of the things
that makes it really hard for weight
loss if your metabolism is quote unquote
slow again think that total input versus
output is low say 2,000 and you want to
drop it by say 500 calories you've
reduced a significant portion of your
caloric intake you're going to feel that
and you've dropped a quarter of your
calories however if you're at 4,000
calories Turn and Burn and we drop you
by
500 now we've only lowered your intake
by a small percentage and so you don't
feel that much of a difference you won't
really feel 3500 calories versus 4,000
calories but you'll feel 15 versus 2,000
even though in both cases is exact 500
calories and so for a lot of people
there is still a huge interest in
understanding and making your overall
metabolism function how you want for
both the short and long term regardless
of whether or not body composition or
body fat is your primary secondary or
even of slight interest to you right now
now I can continue talking about that
Delta and why you want to avoid energy
toxicity but you do at the same time
want to have a high caloric intake but
we'll save those thoughts for another
conversation we want to get really into
today's topic and so what does speeding
up your metabolism even mean and I've
been using a bunch of different terms
thus far on purpose I've tried to throw
out misconceptions I've used the wrong
phrase intentionally because that's how
it's used colloquially that's probably
how you've heard it and that's how
you've thought about it so I've done
that uh with direct intent there we're
going to talk about what those things
mean we're going to talk about what it
actually means to have a fast or slow
metabolism and so let's get into those
very basic parts right now
scientifically metabolism is the net of
all cellular processes in your entire
body so when you're metabolizing
hormones or proteins or energy
substrates like carbohydrates and fat
all of that is combined together to make
up your metabolism so that is a giant
net it is not specifically and only
referring to the calories in versus
calories out what you're burning for
exercise or your body fat composition it
is all things going on that is an
incredibly difficult number to come up
with with it is not a rate it is a total
amount what I mean by that is it's not a
speed this is why I can tell you people
in our field and mind you I've got a PhD
in human
bioenergetics so people in this field
will tell you there is no speed
component here it is a total rate
component and so the analogy I'll give
you here is a car okay now if I had you
driving in your car at 50 m an hour and
we increased you to 70 mph you your
speed went up okay when people think
about boosting their metabolism that's
what they think happens I'm driving
faster and when we say you don't speed
up your metabolism when I tell you yours
is the same speed as mine what I mean is
we're all driving at 50 m hour but at
the same time I also did tell you we can
raise it and that there are some people
who can handle more energy and not gain
as much and so forth that's not a speed
issue what that is is the total amount
of drive time right it is not speeding
up your metabol M it is going through
metabolism more frequently that's
effectively what's happening so it's
driving more often if you drive more
often let's say again the analogy of
speed here we're both driving at 50 mil
per hour you don't speed up or slow down
but I drive for one mile and you drive
for 15 who burned more gas you did
that's exactly what we're talking about
so somebody with a fast metabolism is
someone who's simply driving for 15
miles and someone with a slow metabolism
is somebody who's driving for 5 miles or
2 miles or whatever the case may be that
is incredibly important because we as we
start getting into claims in the field
and misconceptions and improper
marketing they're going to use those
things as tricks and ways to twist you
so easy examples there's plenty of
supplements that you can take that will
quote unquote speed up your metabolism
they will turn it on they will get you
going but they do not result in any
additional fat loss for mechanisms in
which we will cover later and so
understanding the very basic principle
there lets you realize okay great they
can make a certain claim there but in
reality it is what I'm trying to hear is
that product will help me lose fat more
and that will not be the case that is
often what we see and have historically
heard in the magazines in the media with
the supplement companies and so forth
regarding speeding up your metabolism so
now that you understand that you're not
going to fall all a prey to that trick
again so here's what we really mean when
people say I want a faster metabolism or
my metabolism is slow and so they say my
metabolism is too slow or I want it to
go faster what are they really saying
they're generally talking about body
composition I hate to phrase it this way
I didn't want to do it because there's
so much more to metabolism than just
body comp but again this is a very easy
entry point for us so we'll stay here
just so most people can understand so
when they're saying that my metabolism
is slow what they're usually saying
saying is a common about their body
composition they have more fat than they
would like it's hard for them to lose
fat it's hard for them to gain muscle or
the opposite someone who complains of a
fast metabolism is somebody who's having
a hard time gaining muscle I eat and I
eat and I eat and I just can't gain I
eat and I eat I just can't gain so
there's there's complaints on both sides
of the equation example here just to
give you some math let's say both you
and your friend eat 1500 calories a day
and let's say we live in a magical
universe and stress and sleep and all
that is all qued for the only difference
between
you you both add 1,500 calories per day
for 8 weeks one of you loses three lb
the other loses 12 PB that is a real
thing that can and does happen it's easy
then for you to think okay metabolism
Fast Metabolism slow so what's really
happening there is a change in what we
call
TDE e or total daily energy expenditure
when you hear the phrase fast and slow
metabolism or the phrase is I want you
to think total daily energy expenditure
now that has four unique components and
I'll cover in one second but the reality
of it is what could be explaining that
person who lost more weight than you did
or didn't gain as much whether you're in
a choric surplus or caloric deficit it
doesn't matter something in that total
daily energy expenditure was different
for them there is no in that component
that is metabolic speed but that's the
translation all right so boosting
metabolism is really an increase or
decrease in total daily energy
expenditure if you want to look at total
body mass body composition we can look
at this as simply as our energy
expenditure versus our energy intake a
lot of times you'll see this abbreviated
is EI energy intake so I can increase or
decrease my weight by changing either
side of my equation for example if I
increased my total daily energy
expenditure of which I have four ways to
do that four components but if I
increase that and I didn't increase my
intake my body mass will go down or I
could keep my energy expenditure the
same and I could lower my energy intake
okay or combinations of both but that's
honestly what we're what we're talking
about when we're discussing metabolic
speed I'm actually fine with people
saying I've sped up my metabolism as
long as they're using it appropriately
in this context I don't like to use it
but I absolutely get it why most folks
do and so total daily energy expenditure
as I said has four components what are
those four components the first one is
what we call eat eat some people call
this e what we're effectively talking
about is exercise so eat stands for the
exercise activity thermogenesis it's the
calories you burn during exercise e is
energy expenditure it doesn't matter how
you think about this but it's how many
calories did you burn in your workout
for most people that's going to
represent somewhere between 0 to
30% of their total daily energy
expenditure so just to make sure you're
following me of all the calories you
burn throughout the day everything
combined if you don't work out well then
none of their caloric expenditure is
going to be explained by
exercise most people though probably
going to have 10 to 20% % of the
calories they burn throughout the day
coming from exercise folks that are
really training a lot maybe closer to 20
25 or even up to 30% it's hard to get
past 30% you would have to train a ton
but you can generally think 10 20% of
your energy throughout the day coming
from
calories we will talk about this later
but this is one of the reasons why and
and I I will explain very clearly why
this is the wrong thing to think but
this is the fodder some people use to
say things like oh exercise doesn't even
help with fat loss and they're not
entirely wrong here because it's not
explaining the largest part of your
caloric expenditure 10% even for someone
who works out pretty often or pretty
hard 90% of the calories you're burning
are from things not exercised so they're
not completely unfounded though again I
think it's really terrible advice we'll
talk about that and the research on it
in detail later but again component
number one of total daily energy
expenditure is exercise component number
two is similar to eat which is called
neat so it's eat with an n in front of
it it is
non-exercise activity thermal Genesis
this is all the other physical activity
you're doing throughout the day that is
not structured and specific
exercise this is everything from
fidgeting to walking pacing taking the
stairs going uh parking further in the
parking lot so you walk more it is all
of those other things that are still
going to expend calories but they're not
exercise
one of the interesting things about this
is this has often times as much if not a
bigger component of your total energy
expenditure than structured exercise
does people have completely forgotten
about this but the reality of it is it's
going to be somewhere between 5 to 30%
of your
TDE the next two components are what's
called your TEF and I apologize for all
the acronyms here I'm trying to really
make sure we walk you through it I think
you're holding on this far it is the
thermal effect of food this is quite
simply the energies or the heat you
create in response to breaking down food
in your stomach so the reality is when
you eat food items they sit in your
stomach you have to burn some calories
to digest them if you want to think
about it that way and that then creates
some chloric expenditure it's usually
about 8 to 15% of your tte and so if you
add eat neat and TEF up what you have
remaining of that 100% is your rest
testing metabolic rate and that ranges
from about 40% of TDE all the way up to
80% especially in folks that are
sedentary or lowly active so as we get
into this how I'm going to cover the
intervention and the research is which
area of total daily energy expenditure
is each given protocol or intervention
influencing so what can we do to
increase our eat what can we do an
increased neat TEF as well as resting
metabolic rate the reality as I said at
the beginning I think it's best that you
try to implement a well-rounded plan
that influences all four of these
components or at least multiple of them
but if you can't exercise say you're
injured or bedridden or you're in
another scenario where you can't
exercise or whatever the case may be you
have other options and that's why I want
to present all this stuff as so you know
no matter what situation you're in based
on preference or realistic or
feasibility or Effectiveness you can
alter your metabolism in in multiple
Fashions to make sure that your body
composition and overall energy intake is
where you want it to be whether that's
loss gain or maintenance for that matter
today's episode is sponsored by momentus
momentus makes the highest quality
supplements on the market period many of
you know me and you know that I do not
trust the vast majority of supplement
companies and for good reason many
Studies have shown that anywhere between
10 to up to 40% of supplements have
accidental contaminants intentional
alterations mislabeling or other serious
issues but momentus is different I
literally spent years vetting the
company their products and leadership
team before personally officially
partnering with them in 20123 every
single one of moment's products is
third-party tested to ensure quality and
many are even NSF certified for sport
now while I love all of their products
the ones I use the most both personally
and with my clients are what I call the
big three and these are the omega-3 fish
oil creatine and newly improved whey
protein formula these three supplements
have fantastic data supporting their
benefits weight protein forward lean
muscle mass Omega-3s for brain health
and creatine for both muscle and brain
support and they have been shown to be
very safe across basically all
populations of people young old men
women Etc now nobody has to use
supplements and I hope you never feel
pressured to do so but if you're
interested in supplements it's important
that you get them from the highest
quality providers you don't want Mercury
and your fish oil or lead in your way
protein or anything like that so that's
why I stick exclusively to momentus if
you'd like to give momentus a try go to
liv.com perform to get 20% off your
order again that's Liv mous.com perform
to get 20% off as I mentioned a moment
ago exercise calories tends to get most
people's attention when it comes to the
thing you got to do you got to work out
more you got to train harder you got to
burn more
calories I am actually in the the camp
that the caloric expenditure from
exercise is playing a fairly minimal
role in weight management that said
there are a trillion other reasons why
you should exercise even if fat loss is
your only
goal we'll talk about that later but
from a simple caloric expenditure from a
simple boosting metabolism concept
exercise is not playing a massive
component this is one of the few times
in physiology when we can say that hey
exercise is not the biggest hammer we
can swing in this
variable more important is that neat now
that neat as I mentioned somewhere
between 5 and 30% and it is highly
responsive we've actually only known
about neat for 20 or 25 years um James
LaVine has the the famous paper here I
think it was
1999 that thing was published where he
outlined he said oh my gosh this kind of
fidgeting and walking thing feels
completely un necessary or not it can't
contributing that much is really making
a big impact in fact now we know that
neat is likely the most modifiable one
it is ultra responsive it's it's the
governor your body uses when it needs to
dial up energy expenditure it ramps up
neat when it KN needs to dial it back it
ramps it down it is absolutely the
throttle your body is moving completely
unaware of your conscious thought to
regulate overall energy balance we had
no idea of this until again as I
mentioned 20 years or so so which is
very recent
scientifically in that original paper I
think it's really cool because it it's
just going to hammer this point down
what they sort of found was it was
something in the order of the neat
accounted for like a tenfold difference
in fat storage when you overfed now I
can't remember if this was in I think it
was an animal study we certainly if if
you're aware we can put some comments in
the YouTube section to help me out there
but it doesn't matter the point was what
they did is they
overfed the folks or the the animals in
the study and what they realized was
again a tenfold difference in fat
storage based on the animals that
upregulated neat in response to the
overfeeding and I think the correlation
was like 08 correlation of one is a
perfect line cor correlation like 3 or
four is still really important so the
fact that their correlation was like 08
or or more said hey this is basically
exactly what is explaining folks who can
eat more food food again they
intentionally overfed this group I'll
call them folks but probably animals and
the ones that didn't gain the most
amount of weight were the ones that
responded almost perfectly for 50 extra
calories eaten 50 extra calories a neat
I made that number up but you get the
point right the ones that had 50 extra
calories of food 10 extra calories in
eat were the ones who gained the most
weight and this is when our field
completely turned the attention and said
oh my gosh it's not the 100 calories
you're burning in your workout it is
really whose physiology can match or is
mismatched with their energy intake and
their need and that is clearly one of
the bigger than drivers of the faster
metabolism person versus the slower
metabolism person to be really clear
here what they're suggesting here is the
folks who appear to have a faster
metabolism are the ones whose bodies
upregulate neat in response to
upregulations or increases in energy
intake the ones who seem to have a
slower metabolism are the opposite their
body doesn't have a tight understanding
or communication loop with energy intake
so even though they ramp up calories in
they don't see a huge increase in
caloric expenditure through neat and
that thus then probably explains when
you and your friend both increased your
calories by 1,000 calories yet you
gained two pounds and she gained 15
pounds or whatever the case may be so
that's why I make sure wanted to make
sure we neat because it has that
incredible role and we will talk about
what happens in different short and
long-term scenarios with neat so we can
really understand what we need to do to
manage it and to take the most advantage
of it regardless of whether we're fast
or slow or in between metabolic speed
person now the next two components that
we talked about outside of eat and neat
are the thermal effect of food and
resting metabolic rate the thermal
effect of food as I mentioned is
somewhere between like 8 to 15% of your
total daily energy
expenditure what this is is how much
calories or how many calories you burn
breaking down food and that differs
based on your macronutrient in fact the
reality of it is it differs based on
your food preparation so if you get a
whole steak as an example in bites
versus that same exact cut of meat but
preg ground up you'll see a difference
in thermal effect and it makes total
sense if your body is having to work to
digest that whole big chunk because you
didn't chew it well for example of steak
it will take it more calories to break
it down however if you pre- digest it
I.E blend it up chop it up then it's
less work more chemical bonds have been
broken so your body will it'll be a very
small
amount basically negligible but
conceptually you're seeing the point
here right your body won't have to spend
as many calories to break it down so the
thermal effect of food is different
based on the macronutrient profile for
example fat has an effect of somewhere
between 0 and
2% now there are pros and cons what this
means is if you eat 100 calories of fat
you're probably going to digest absorb
and assimilate a basically all 100
calories this makes it highly effective
for a lot of different things
particularly for storage for keeping the
calories around if you're in a survival
situation if you want to use an extreme
here again it doesn't matter I know most
of us are rarely in a survival situation
but just use it as the thought concept
here I don't want to waste a bunch of my
calories of my food on breaking it down
I want to preserve as many of those
calories from the small food that I was
able to procure and keep those in my
body so fat has a huge Advantage there
however from a weight management
perspective most of us being in a
position where we have too much access
to food rather than not
enough that can actually be a little bit
detrimental because now now I'm going to
definitely take on all the calories that
I eat contrast that to carbohydrates and
protein carbohydrates are a little bit
higher thermal effect is usually between
5 and 10% what that means let's just say
again you ate 100 calories of
carbohydrate you might burn five or 10
calories breaking them down and so the
net result in your body is 95 or 90 and
this is one of the main reasons why not
to get us on a tangent here off track
when people say things like oh calories
in calories out don't matter or I tried
that and it didn't work there's a lot of
reasons that explain that but the
thermal effective food is one of them
100 calories of carbohydrate versus fat
versus protein just thermal effect alone
is going to result in a different amount
of energy absorption and so calories in
calories out is still perfectly
explaining that you just didn't
fundamentally realize that the calories
out portion is is changed based on the
macronutrient because of the thermal
effect so I have a separate video on
YouTube it's called the quality versus
quantity I think the great calorie
debate or something it's an hour or too
long you can see exactly what I'm
talking about you can see some of the
papers and plenty of examples and we'll
have that Linked In the show notes so if
I lost you there I apologize but if not
just trust me so to come back to this
the thermal effect of protein is the
highest of these three by far 15
30% and so right off the Gaze here
you're probably intuitively thinking
okay wait a minute then if I eat 100
calories of protein I may only have a
net of 70 or 80 or 85 with that same 100
calories in my mouth in the form of
carbohydrates and fat would have a much
higher yield and so you can increase
your
metabolism I'm going to lose you a
little bit on math here right you can
increase your metabolism I'm I'm for
those of you just listening I'm air
quoting right now by eating more protein
because you're going to actually be
eating the same amount of calories as
your
friend but the net result of calories
you keep on board is much lower
Therefore your caloric intake is lower
and therefore your body composition
would change because of that so this is
a case where it it made you feel like it
gave you the perception of the
metabolism being higher or faster
because your net body composition result
result was better body fat was lower
even though you made the same calories
and you can't understand why cuz you
were calorie matched I will walk you
through specific examples with numbers
on this stuff later if I just lost you
in a kind of a bunch of negative
positives up down things there if not I
think you get the concept I hope you do
at this point so thermal effective food
is an important
consideration last caveat there before
we move on to resting metabolic rate and
that is those numbers I gave you are
very
rough when I say carbohydr yes it
depends on the typee of
carbohydrate uh a scoop of Honey will
not give you the same thermal effect as
a potato so the the way that you prepare
your food the preparation how they're
combined together starches versus
glucose versus monosaccharide yes all
this definitely matters but that's why
that numbers a range 15 to 30 for
protein 5 to 10 for carbs 0 to two for
fat so don't get Ultra caught up in
those numbers just think of it as cons
Cally um burning a small but not
irrelevantly more calories for digesting
protein then carbohydrates and then
certainly versus
fat our fourth and final component here
your resting M metabolic rate is the
thing people most associate with their
metabolic
speed somewhere between 40 to 70% and
generally you can think about this as
folks that are highly Physically Active
whether that be from exercise or from
neat because they're burning more
calories from there by default the
number of calories they're burning as a
percentage of their total daily Ingy
expenditure goes down so highly
Physically Active people their resting
metabolic rate is sometimes like only 40
or 50% of their total energy expenditure
as you get less active all the way up to
sedentary or completely inactive people
that resting molic rate may explain 70
to 80% of your energy expens man want to
be really careful here thus far I've
only explained these as a percentage of
your total output I'm not even talking
about increasing or decreasing total
output so just as a percentage
there if neat is not the most modifiable
one resting metabolic rate is this the
two places that you have the most short
and long-term ability to interact and
change often times people will talk
about resting metabolic rate or you'll
also hear the term basil metabolic rate
for purposes today I'm going to continue
to use resting metabolic rate but I want
you to be aware these are not the exact
same thing I don't think it's Ultra
important you know the difference today
but just in case you're wondering
they're both functionally measuring
energy output in the body but they do it
in a little bit of a different way
technically basil metabolic rate is the
number of calories your body needs to
perform very basic functions at rest so
if you laid there on a table nothing was
in your system you were awake how many
calories is your body burning to pump
your blood circulate your hormones keep
your brain alive so on and so forth it
is the minimum to keep you alive and
that's why they call it basil metabolic
rate resting metabolic rate is the same
thing but it is the actual amount of
calories you're burning at any given
moment your basil metabolic rate is
pretty stable we'll talk about how to
increase that a little bit later your
resting metabolic rate is completely
responsive to what you just did so if I
gave you let's say
caffeine your resting metabolic rate if
I sat you on a table after gesting
caffeine your resting metabolic rate
would go up however that's not your
basil metabolic rate because your basil
simply said what did I burn before or
outside of the increase
in response to caffeine so because we're
talking about ways to increase metabolic
rate I'm going to mostly focus on
resting metabolic rate now as you'll see
in our investigate discussion we can
measure this a lot of different ways but
just so you know what you're asking for
I'm jumping ahead of the gun a little
bit here but since we're on it I want to
get it out now a basil metabolic rate
test has to be done after at least a
12-hour fast as I just alluded to you
can't eat before it you can't can't have
your coffee or tea or anything else you
can't be sleeping or listening to music
it needs to truly be a baseline if
that's what you're interested in a
resting molic rate is way less stringent
you can do it under any condition you
want you have to understand how to
interpret it that way but it is
functionally different there so the
usefulness in my opinion of resting Mal
metabolic rate is probably a little bit
higher because it's a better
understanding of what's happening on a
day-to-day basis or what's going on in
your real life scenario where basil
metabolic rate though is more controlled
it's more scientific and it does help
you understand what's really happening
in your body if you care so that said
let's talk really quickly about how to
measure these things if you want to know
your metabolic rate your B BMR or your
RMR how do I get these things tested
from the highest quality gold standard
all the way down to the cheapest and I
can't afford or have access to a lab
what do I do as I mentioned a moment ago
if you really want BMR testing done
please contact the lab that you're going
to work with you're going to have to do
it in that setting and make sure that
you follow their exact protocols and I'm
saying this because I've had a lot of
clients that I coach personally do this
in the past and their numbers come back
completely funky and I ask did you
follow all the exact recipe that the
place told you to prior to and they
don't and so everyone does it a little
bit differently but almost always if you
are going to a lab say Dr Mike ormsby's
Lab at Florida State who offers service
like this for somewhere neigh of like
$50 to $75 or something like that they
will usually send you a list or an email
that says hey the night before do a b
and c and don't do this in the morning
and so forth follow those things
perfectly this is not a blood draw where
you can kind of get away with some
different things everything that you're
going to do through your sleep to the
music you're listening to and number of
other factors could influence the number
and if you want good data we've got to
have excellent control so if you're
going to do that follow those rules so I
just sort of alluded to it but the gold
standard here would be to get a test
done in a laboratory you can find them
all over the place I would personally
nothing against anybody but personally
encourage you to do this in a scientific
laboratory if you can there's plenty of
clinics and popup facilities that do it
and some are good just my again personal
experience having coached a lot of
athletes and a lot of non-athletes I
don't always have super strong trust in
these places they don't calibrate their
machines often and so on and so forth so
if you go to a research facility that
does this for a living they have the
scientific standard and they've done
thousands of these over years you're
just a little bit more likely to get
better data so contact your local
University if you can if they have an
exercise physiology department or
anything like that and there's a
reasonable chance that they offer such
testing and again the price point is you
know call it $100 plus or minus or a
little bit lower so that's the best way
to do it there's also some portable
devices coming on board I've tried a
number of these I don't love them yet
but I'm actually pretty confident they
will get better in the near future so I
don't have a product to recommend to you
right now because of that reason but I
have hope for that in the future there's
also other ways you can go about this
there are products that I know for
example one called colorify where you
can buy doubly labeled water they'll
ship it to you you can drink it you will
collect your urine chip it back in uh
doubly labeled water for the record is
the scientific one of the scientific
gold standards and so this is fairly
expensive I think I paid
$1,000 for it um if you I don't know
like we've We've ran with through some
people some of it was okay some of it
was really good some of it wasn't as
good I actually I'm assuming the price
will get cheaper over time it'll get
better over time so if you really want
to know the exact number you're at and
you have a little bit more to osble
income perhaps a company like chlori
which I have no ties to whatsoever I
bought it a normal price that everyone
else did or if you're needing a little
bit lower price point or have other
interest maybe a lab is the way to go in
terms of
wearables you're generally not a good
solution there's a lot of data on this
you will find some reports and so papers
that suggest a caloric expenditure
estimates from a watch or a ring or a
strap are okay most of them are not good
in general they overestimate caloric
expenditure we've seen this for decades
now this originally started with the
treadmills and the bikes and the stair
climbers in gyms I tell you you burned 1
th000 calories in your workout and
almost ubiquitously universally they
overestimated it we've seen the same
basic thing with wearables they
generally overestimate it by honestly an
amount that makes it not worth it if
it's off by 15% that's your entire
margin of error that's your window of
opportunity to lose weight so at that
point how useful is it so if you want to
use something like that or you already
have one that's great maybe it does
track well for you awesome but I I
wouldn't put a ton of stock in that if
you really are concerned about this I
would go to one of those other two
options or the third option which is
entirely free and that is using
scientifically validated prediction
equations these have been around for
over 50 years and actually more than
that the the one that we have used
probably the most is called the Harris
Benedict I'm pretty sure that's about a
hundred years old actually actually I'm
quite positive that was from the
1920s originally it's been around a long
time been validated in men women young
old all kinds of different demographics
we use it a lot because uh there's
actually a friend of mine Andrew yum at
mail Clinic has has published a paper
quite recently finding that the Harris
Benedict was more effective and more
accurate I should say for specifically
athletes and so whether or not you're an
athlete it's probably not the defining
Factor but this is generally probably
the thing that is better for people who
are maybe higher in muscle mass and
higher in physical activity so don't
worry about the athlete part but just
think if you have more muscle than the
average person and you're more active
maybe this equation is better for you
there are plenty of them if you poke
around they are almost all free you can
take your information put in then uh you
can add additional physical activity
modifiers what I mean by that is they'll
ask you questions like are you lowly
physically active so take these numbers
in the equation and multiply them by 1.0
are you moderate maybe multiply it by
1.2 are you highly active are you
extremely active 1.3 modifier so on and
so forth if I lost you don't worry about
it if you again pull these things up
they'll walk you through it you can
enter some basic information about your
age height weight and so forth and then
it'll give you a rough estimate of your
energy expenditure so they're going to
get you in the right ballpark
if you don't even want to do that the
easiest cheap way to do it is just test
retest what I mean by that is measure
your body weight hold as many variables
constant as you can and then see what
happens if you're losing weight you're
in a deficit if you're gaining weight
you're in a surplus I've used that more
than almost anything to be honest with
you I I don't spend a lot of time on
Harris benedict for high performers
because ultimately I want to care about
well are you going down if you're losing
weight too fast and you're not feeling
as recovered your performance isn't good
energy is going down then I know we've
underestimated calories and we'll bring
them back up if you're not losing weight
you get the idea there if you're gaining
weight well then you get the idea or
you're not gaining weight and we're
trying to gain weight so it's a little
bit self-correcting as my point there
but nonetheless if you want to get it
tested there's a handful of different
options at different price points and
that are available at least here in
America plenty of options and then
certainly the prediction equations are
open to anyone in the world you can
explore and use what is best for you in
your situation today's episode is
sponsored by element element is an
electrolyte drink mix that has an ideal
electrolyte ratio of sodium potassium
and magnesium but no sugar hydration is
critical to Performance both physical
and mental performance countless Studies
have shown that even a slight degree of
dehydration even as small as 1% can lead
to decreases in physical output and
mental performance we also know that
electrolytes are critical to proper
hydration which I've been harping on for
years but you can't do that proper
hydration by only drinking water you
need to get the right amount of
electrolytes in the right ratios and
that's why I'm a huge fan of element in
fact many of you will probably remember
that I featured element in my YouTube
series on optimizing hydration nearly 5
years ago I featured element in these
videos because they're blend of 1,000 mg
of sodium 200 Mig potassium and 60 Mig
of magnesium really is unique and
different than any other electrolyte on
the market and it has great scientific
support I use element constantly
particularly when I'm sweating a lot and
I routinely make it a part of my
client's optimization programs if you'd
like to try element you can go to drink
LM nt.com perform to claim a free
element sample pack with the pures of
any element drink mix again that's drink
LM nt.com perform to claim a free sample
pack today's episode is also brought to
you by Parker University Parker is the
only University in the world dedicated
exclusively to Human Performance it's
also my new academic home I first heard
of Parker after attending their neuroon
seminar and was stunned I've been to
countless clinics and conferences and
nobody is even close to Parker Seminars
the speakers the setup and the total
experience are frankly jaw-dropping all
their seminars are great but the
upcoming Las Vegas show which is going
down March 20th through 22nd is going to
be extra special it's featuring speakers
like doctors Andrew huberman Tommy wood
Gab a lion and more but on top of that
I'm personally hosting a co- seminar at
the same time so imagine going to a
phenomenal lecture on how the nerve
system works then popping over and
lifting some weights with me personally
grabbing lunch and then settling in for
a talk on how NASA scientist Cody
Burkhart is preparing human bodies for
Life on Mars tickets for this incredible
event are on sale now at a special rate
of only
$599 but this price will increase as the
dates get closer so do not wait and yes
you heard that right $599 Get You full
access to the entire Parker seminar expo
hall nightlife and social events plus
two full days of learning and lifting
weights with me in the gym and my friend
Dan Garner to see the exact schedule
list of speakers and get signed up visit
Parker seminars.com one more time that's
Parker seminars.com I can't wait to see
you there so now that we've got this
thing tested you've got your data one
way or the other how do you interpret it
well let's remember resting metabolic
rate alone is you know 40 to 80% of your
total daily energy expenditure and so we
don't want to make decisions about all
of our caloric intake based only on
resting metabolic rate we've got to have
some sense of thermal effect energy
expenditure and neat this is why I'll go
back to the previous conversation about
saying what's actually happening in your
body weight and composition is the
ultimate answer because it factors
everything in by default but nonetheless
let's just talk about resting metabolic
rate I don't know of any way at this
point to measure neat outside of
something like a step count and this is
where a wearable or a Tracker would be
effective it's going to miss a lot of
stuff fidgeting chewing gum things like
that so they're not going to be great
but if you wanted to have a physical
activity thing and get you maybe 80% of
the way there 70% I don't know that's a
probably a pretty good use energy
expenditure during exercise is quite
simple a a heart rate monitor a strap
preferably is the best way if you have a
wearable that's fine again they tend to
significantly overestimate caloric
expenditure but if you have a heart rate
strap that's very likely to tell you the
real answer in the real number that is
still the gold standard the Garmin the
polers the ones that you buy off the
shelf are the same ones we buy in our
lab and have bought a button I can't
tell you how many hundreds of polar
straps in my career and so that's one
example of a technology in a product
that is the exact same in the lab as it
is on the consumer shelf that will tell
you your real num so if you really do
care about caloric expenditure I would
not use the data from the machine the
treadmill the bike or anything like that
use a heart rate monitor use any
situation or setup that you'd like and
that's going to give you really strong
data about where you're at all right so
again can't do much about thermal
effective food can't do much about neat
outside of
maybe a step count or accelerometer
something like that in terms of energy
expenditure we use the heart rate
monitor in terms of resting metabolic
rate though here's what we know about it
the range is enormous I have seen people
as little as a thousand to well over
3,000 this sometimes tracks with body
size generally but not always such to
say I've seen people that are the same
size with with the resting metal ball at
rate of a th000 and someone else their
exact same size that's at 2500 or the
inverse so it tracks roughly bigger
people gen to have a bigger RMR but not
specifically enough to where it's useful
if you're actually trying to adjust
based on calories men are generally a
scooch higher for resting metabolic rate
1600 to 1800 is a pretty common number
you'll find collectively in literature
women more like 1,400 to 1700
okay now remember this is just resting
metabolic rate not total daily energy
expenditure and one of the things that
you'll see happen is the differences
between both sex and age in resting
metabolic rate are explained almost
entirely by lean muscle mass and by
entirely I mean up to
80% so I've kind of answered one of our
questions for later now but I'll hit it
since we're here does your resting
abolic rate change or go down with age
and the answer is not nearly as much as
you think if it does it's explained
almost entirely by lack or loss of
muscle mass we will talk in more detail
later about the men versus women aspect
of that but one more time if you equate
for muscle mass we see very little very
very little differences in resting
metabolic rate between those two and so
off the cuff we we don't have numbers
that I'm going to give you here that are
men versus women for these exact reasons
so I will cover the numbers in one
second but if you're wondering is he
talking about are these numbers for men
or these numbers for women or why didn't
he talk about women I'm not going to
differentiate because again we have
evidence that suggest it's not going to
be differ so we don't need to specify it
that
way so the things that ultimately
influence your resting metabolic rate in
terms of interpreting that I break them
into into controllable and
uncontrollable factors the latter are
things like your height your age as we
talked about your gender as we talked
about neither of those probably
influence it as much as you think but
there are other things clearly your
genetics your ethnicity you can't do
anything about these and they will
absolutely change your your Baseline but
the list of controllable is far larger
and we'll spend all of our time today on
that and that's everything from your
activity level your nutrition and
supplements and diets and drugs and
hormone concentrations activity levels
the environment you're in the
temperature that you're around and so on
and so forth so there's a lot of things
that are going to influence it and it
changes based on the day there's an
awesome paper that came out really
recently uh Margaret Jones was a part of
this um Andrew yagen was a part of this
but it's called differences in body fat
and athletes categorize by resting
metabolic rate a bit of a a mouthful
there but the reason I'm bringing it up
now is it gave a table of percentile
rankings of resting molic rate for men
and women that range from the bottom
fifth percentile to the 10th to the 20th
and so on and so forth all the way up to
90th percentile that show that paper is
available on the show notes you can pull
up this exact table I'm looking at so if
you go get it tested or go get it
estimated and you want to look at this
table you can see exactly where you rank
one more time this was done in athletes
but I don't want you to think about this
as oh it doesn't apply to you because
you don't play a sport just think of
this as a probably more muscular than
the average person and pretty highly
Physically Active the data are probably
then going to explain pretty closely
what's going on with you but they had a
couple of interesting findings from this
and I'll walk through the numbers here
in one second but what they found was uh
expressing resting modol rate relative
to body weight or at least adjusting for
independent
factors accounted for way more of a
difference in body size than not so it's
allowed for more favorable comparisons
and I know I maybe just jumbled that up
a little bit there it was probably less
clear than I could be but what I'm
effectively saying is if you were to
take a normal chart and just Googled
resting metabolic rate you'll get
numbers if you're highly physically
active and athletic I think those
numbers are different and I think Andrew
and Margaret's paper showed clearly that
they are and so I'm bringing this paper
up now in this section because I think
this table is a better one to use for
these people and I know a lot of you
listening are pretty physically active
so you're probably more likely to fall
into this category than you are someone
who doesn't exercise and with high
amounts of obesity or things like that
and so I like this table better it is a
better resource rather than pulling up
chat GPT or something else and just sort
of asking what's a good metabolic rate
these numbers are significantly better
so what are you looking at okay let's
Capstone this a little bit for the
bottom F percentile if you're resting
metabolic rate and now again we're
expressing this relative to body size a
low the bottom fifth percentile you're
looking at in the neighborhood of about
22 calories per
kilogram the highest 95th percentile is
about 31 32
33 kcals per kilogram again the table
breaks down everything else in between
but that's a pretty good number to think
about a lot of the times you'll see
resting metabolic rate reported simply
as a number like I've done earlier 1,500
calories 1,200 calories the more
accurate way though is to do it again
Andrew's paper showed
this but is to do it based on how much
muscle size you have and that's why
you're seeing numbers like 25 27 if
you're like what the heck it's divided
by their body weight so if you wear if
you weigh 80
kilos and you have a resting metabolic
rate of
20 which which would be really really
low K Cals per kilogram 20 * 80 would be
1,600 and you would have a resting
metabolic total resting metabolic rate
of 1,600 K calories so hopefully that
math made a little bit more sense but
the the argument in this paper was quite
compelling and I think this is the
better approach to it uh if you followed
along with that with that business now
taken care of it's finally time for us
to get to our third and final eye and
that is intervene we need to break this
up into a couple of categories I'm going
to call them acute and chronic and what
I'm really meaning here is what are
things that will change your total daily
energy expenditure in any four of the
categories that are transient versus
those that are going to make a
longlasting
permanent change couple of examples to
make this tangible the way that you want
to think about these acute markers are
these aren't necessarily establishing
say a new resting metabolic rate there's
no Baseline so if you uh example I gave
at the beginning was caffeine and we'll
just stick with that because it's easy
to understand if you take caffeine right
right now your resting metabolic rate
will go up it's not going to influence
your thermal effect of food makes sense
but it may make you more physically
active so it may result in you burning
more energy through neat or you may be
more motivated and able to work out
harder so your energy expenditure can go
up so you can see a single acute Factor
influence three of your four variables
and that that particular case
however you wake up tomorrow morning
your neat your energy expenditure and
your resting metabolic rate are going to
be right back down to normal Baseline
and so chronic changes though are things
like is your basil metabolic rate that
resting metabolic rate now higher day to
day to day to day there's a lot of
things and you could really have an
almost endless list that will
acutely increase or decrease one of the
four factors but most people when we're
going all the way back to the beginning
if you're thinking I want a faster
metabolism because I want to burn more
calories and have a
more efficient or effective system have
a different body composition however
people interpret that you're most likely
thinking I just wish I burn more
calories doing nothing that's
effectively chronic changes so can I
increase my resting metabolic rate so
that I'm burning more calories sitting
around right Al talk about how things
that necessarily boost your basil
metabolic rate or rather your acute
metabolic rate won't necessarily always
translate into body fat loss but wanting
to establish acute Factor versus chronic
factors now they are both important
certainly things that will increase your
acute resting metabolic rate for example
if repeated days and days and days and
then therefore weeks and weeks and weeks
will simply result ideally and more
calories burn which will then increase
total daily energy expenditure but that
distinction is important kind of what
are going to be requiring more active
continually practices versus ones that
are passive and sustained for a long
time that's acute versus chronic let's
start with the acute list all right and
we'll go through both sections by the
way acute and chronic going through each
individual Factor TEF neat eat and
resting metabolic rate so starting with
the
cute if you look at energy expenditure
from
exercise clearly here you want to burn
more calories do more work that's a
simple as it could possibly be but
probably the more interesting thing here
is Are there specific types or forms or
modes of exercise that burn more
calories more efficiently than others
and so if all you're interested in here
is caloric expenditure which ones should
I choose well ultimately I'd say it
doesn't matter that much pick the one
you're going to have the most effort in
that has the lowest risk of injury for
you the one that you'll be the most
sustained that you'll have the highest
throughput with with and effort and
repeatability and that's the long answer
that's the real answer but I know that's
not what you're fishing for here the
reality of it is aerobic exercise
conditioning exercise endurance exercise
however you like to term this almost
always burns more calories than strength
training type of exercise I'm a strength
training guy I love it I like lifting
weights I greatly prefer it and this is
one of the cases though where the
caloric burn is just not that high the
honest reality if you were to try and in
fact I've I've spoken with colleagues in
preparation for the show about this that
have ran studies like this in the lab I
know of one person who's trying to
figure this out and the amount of
strength training you have to do to
match caloric output from a say steady
state or even interval based
conditioning or endurance workout it's
really challenging I remember a cred
student a long time ago and my faculty
member who was running the lab was very
adamant about this and I was like no way
no way because I was very much focused
on strength training is better than
cardio for everything and we directly
went in the lab and tested this
sometimes behind his back sometimes with
him there and we just never got close we
never got close burning the calories
lifting no matter what style of lifting
we did circuit training hard lifting uh
bodybuilding stuff tons of high volume
and then you sit on a bike for 45
minutes and you just smash the the
calorie output
so that doesn't mean I'm saying only do
endurance work or that it is better for
all things or that is better for fat
loss but if the only variable we're
looking at here is more caloric
expenditure almost always the endurance
side of the equation will win out to the
strength training side of the equation
right there's dozens of other benefits
of why you want to
uh lift and and do a combination of
these probably for most effective
long-term weight loss but calories will
not be it in fact as I talked about
earlier goric expenditure overall with
exercise is much lower than what many
people realize and so it's not a huge
component of TDE so why we're going to
keep this part of it short in general
though one thing we can say is people
who lift
weights very routinely lose less muscle
when in a caloric deficit so one of the
major reasons why you would want to lift
weights if you're trying to lose fat is
not the calories but to preserve or even
slightly increase if possible and it is
possible by the way to lose fat and gain
muscle under certain
circumstances that's the reason why
you'd want to do it so the calories
great you can burn 100 you can burn 150
200 that's amazing but you want to do it
for those reasons of preservation or
even increasing muscle mass we'll talk
about that down the road here about why
that's critical to successful fat loss
but if you just simply look at the
randomized control trials look at the
systematic reviews and meta analyses
people that lift weights as a part of
their fat loss strategy are often times
more successful in the short and long
term meaning they keep the weight off
longer now nothing's
perfect keeping weight loss off forever
is a hard challenge but more likely than
not if you incorporate strength training
into that equation you're more likely to
have a successful maintenance or
permanent loss of that fat I think I've
made that point by now let's go ahead
and move on to the next concept I talked
about endurance and I talked about
strength training what about something
in the middle high-intensity interval
training is one that comes up commonly
and there's good reason for it it's
great it's awesome super effective but
there's also some misconceptions here we
need to clarify some of the things up
that we've heard a lot and frankly
things I've said in the past that not
necessarily wrong but they're probably
exaggerating the point here so as we
mentioned the endurance side of the
equation is probably better at burning
calories during the acute exercise than
strength training however post exercise
what differentiates those two is the
caloric expenditure after the workout is
done if you do moderate to low intensity
steady state work basically as soon as
you stop exercising or within a few
minutes your caloric expenditure goes
right back down to Baseline what's
happening is you start working out you
start burning more calories to match the
calories needed to move but as soon as
you go down to rest you come back down
to Baseline when you strength train and
specifically more when you do higher
intensity interval stuff whether that's
with weights and a kettle bell or
pushing a sled or running Sprints or any
combination we have a phenomenon called
excess post exercise oxygen consumption
we summarize that as Epoch what we're
referring to there is the extra oxygen
consumption that happens after exercise
has been completed the easy way to
conceptualize this when you done if
you're done cycling for 20 minutes at
50% of your heart rate seconds later
your heart rate's back to normal your
breathing's back to normal however if
you did a killer out of intervals you're
going to be huffing and puffing for many
many many more minutes
afterwards even after your respiratory
rate and your heart rate feels like it's
back down to normal you will continue to
be breathing higher than normal for
potentially hours if not much longer
five to 8 to 10 hours after that
exercise and so that is the excess post
exercise oxygen consumption you're
continuing to breathe in that is burning
calories the reason you're doing that is
for a a phenomenon that is not
necessarily important right now but the
reality of it is that is real and so
when you want to account foror
expenditure from exercise with that form
of exercise you have to account for the
calories burned post exercise you can't
simply look at what you burn in the
workout you have to continue to track
the calories you're burning outside of
that some people will refer to this then
as increasing your metabolism or resting
metabolic rate I have it here under the
eat section because it's not really
increasing resting metabolic rate it's
just a carryover you're kind of
basically just continuing to burn
calories from the exercise after you
finish fin it now this is true Epoch is
real it is much higher and it pretty
much tracks with exercise intensity the
higher the intensity the more Epoch but
the reality of it is it's not that many
calories we used to think it was several
hundred calories and so say you did an
interval workout you burn 200 calories
in the workout you might burn an extra
150 in Epoch but it is substantially
lower than that uh you're probably
looking at something more on the
borderline of 30 50 calories
kind of depends there's a large range
there and so it's not irrelevant it all
adds up eventually I'll leave that up to
you to decide whether not 30 or 50
calories in the couple of hours post
exercise matters maybe it's a little bit
higher but it's certainly not several
hundred calories in most circumstances I
share all this information not to confer
you one mode of exercise is better than
another for energy expenditure but to
actually share with you sort of the pros
and cons so that you can make this fit
your system you like I personally prefer
a combination of all three of them what
I like about the lower intensity steady
state stuff is it burns a lot of
calories number one and the recovery is
really high so it doesn't take much out
of your system you can repeat it and
therefore do it often what I like about
the strength training is a preservation
of muscle it isn't as repetitive and
hard for some people mentally to get in
there but I'm not going to get a ton of
calories out of it what I like about the
intervals is it's a short time domain it
has
sucks out your recovery window prob
quite a bit though it's it's tough to
recover from but you get the benefit of
the epoch as well so I like to use all
three of them but use what you feel best
in your CC circumstances and preferences
our next variable then is your
neat this is anything you think can help
you move and be a little bit more active
throughout the day this could be things
like standing desks most of the research
is going to suggest they're going to
burn an additional 100 to 200 calories
per day kind of is a range that number
will be higher the more you're standing
it'll be higher the more you weigh but
that's a pretty standard number one
would see so helpful but again it's not
a th calories per day it's not an
enormous amount you don't have to
necessarily do them all day either by
the way this is something that I thought
Kelly Starrett did a great job of many
years ago telling people and helping us
he had a wonderful book on this topic
but you don't have to go all or none
with just to say you don't have to go
all standing desk all day you can stand
and sit and move about that's personally
how I do it I'll Stand I'll sit I'll go
up and down so maybe I'm burning an
extra 50 calories or 100 calories per
day but this would be considered neat
other things that have gotten more
popular of recent are treadmill desks I
had an adviser a long time ago uh
probably almost 20 years ago who was
really into this stuff he had a
treadmill for his desk I think he set it
at 1 mile per hour you could do some
basic math there if you do 1 mile per
hour for 1 hour a day you've walked one
mile it's about 150 250 calories
depending on your size so again you
don't have to be walking all day I have
a ton of friends who do this I don't
have one personally but anytime I can
walk during meetings that's what I do
and I have a lot of friends who will do
that so maybe you'll do it not when
you're maybe typing or writing or doing
things like that but you're in meetings
you're on zooms and if you're walking at
a very very very low speed it's almost
imperceptible you don't notice it and
you scratch out 100 calories here 50
calories here 75 there and that's going
to add up pretty substantially over time
lots of other ways you can do
it we've talked about exercise snacks
before we've talked uh about at the
beginning of the show you know taking
the stairs more these things never
really excited me because you're like oh
I burned 50 calories I walked more
throughout the day but the reality of it
is I actually had a client who did six
15minute walks throughout the day and
that was his entire exercise he couldn't
do any other stuff didn't want to do it
he felt good he did six 15minute walks
per day that's about 400 calories so
that's actually it's quite substantial
and honestly far more calories than most
people are burning during their really
hard strength training workout so you
don't have to be that extreme you can do
three five minute walks a day three 10-
minute walks a day my friends Dan ordine
has been a huge component of three 10
minute walks a day morning noon and
night you do something like that you're
easily going to hit a couple hundred
maybe even 300 calories and that is
stuff that you're not going to get
fatigued from it you can do it when
you're tired you can do it when you're
sick you can do it in all kinds of
scenarios and you can keep that neat a
little bit higher which will build up
over time and make a big impact on your
overall energy expenditure and body
composition our third variable here is
thermal effective food and this one's
pretty simple you can number one eat
more total food the more food you bring
in the more energy you're going to burn
on digesting and absorbing
food but anyone who's paying attention
right now was be like well wait a minute
sure I ate a thousand extra calories and
so yes I burned a 100 more calories
breaking down food but I also then still
had 900 additional calories and so we'll
hear this theme come up multiple times
but in this area of boosting metabolism
you have to consider
the whole impact on your system and so
you could theoretically just eat more
calories you'll have a higher chloric
expenditure from thermal effect but
that's not probably getting you the
ultimate fat loss result that you're
thinking of so that is one thing you
could do another thing you can do here
is keeping your calories the same but
increasing the percentage of your
calories that come from protein now I
said that very specifically I did not
want to tell you just to eat more
protein
because it's the same mistake I just
made a second ago I kind of set you up
for that if I tell you eat more protein
and you just use that and increase total
caloric intake you're not going to see a
change in body composition because you
burned more calories breaking down the
protein but you had more total calories
and so the correct way to approach this
is a higher percentage of your calories
come from protein which means you
increase your protein intake but then
you reduce
your carbohydrate intake your fat intake
or combination of both you hear this
message a lot it's very common and
popular and for good
reason I personally prefer to recommend
protein as a total amount in terms of
total amount of grams per day and fats
and carbohydrates as a percentage of
your caloric intake and this is exactly
why I want you to hit your protein
targets and we can play with the rest of
your calories from fats and protein but
this is how we maximize thermal effect
and so if you and I are both eating
2,000 calories and you're at 10% protein
and I'm at 40% protein well now I'm
going to have a huge win because I'm
burning so many more calories of that
same number in the form of thermal
effect so that's how you get the most
Advantage out of thermal effect not just
upping protein intake I hear people say
this a lot and I know what they're
trying to say but I wanted to clarify
that because it confuses a lot of people
and they're just say hey man I I
increased my protein by 80 gram a day
and I didn't lose any weight and I'm
like ah yeah calories still matter what
they meant to say was the percentages of
your total chloric intake is the better
approach there another sneaky benefit to
increasing that protein intake by
percentage is it often times will reduce
your total caloric
intake handful of the other topics we're
going to cover will do the same thing
and so when we're looking at strategies
to regulate total daily energy intake
we're not I'm trying to get multiple
wins in one long-winded way here of
saying even if I held your calories
constant and I up that percentage of
protein the research is going to
indicate likely you will
spontaneously reduce your caloric intake
by 3 to 500 calories so I get a double
win here I get this increased thermal
effect but in reality unless you're in a
controlled scientific study there's a
good chance you'll just spontaneously
reduce your calorie intake and that's
because protein is more satiating means
it makes you feel more full not always
the case but a lot of people will have
that response it's well documented in
the literature and so from a direct
calorie win thermal effect great but
probably the bigger benefit is that
indirect you don't feel as hungry you
feel more full and so you just probably
eat less total food which will have the
perception of feeling like your
metabolism sped up wow I'm eating the
same Foods I'm eating all the time I'm
eating till I'm satiated all the time
I'm not starving or hungry but I'm
losing more weight my metabolism must
have sped up well no you just increased
or decreased chloric intake but it felt
like that right another sneaky trick
here to boosting your metabolism if you
will today's episode is sponsored by ag1
ag1 is a vitamin mineral drink with
probiotics prebiotics and adaptogens
initially I was extremely skeptical of
ag1 as I am with all supplement
companies but after months of
discussions with their lead nutrition
scientist and the general team at ag1
I've been impressed by a1's commitment
to sourcing the highest quality
ingredients and constantly updating
their formulas to have the right
ingredients in the optimal amounts ag1
also rigorously test their products to
ensure that every single batch is free
of ban substances allergens heavy metals
microbes pesticides herbicides residual
solvents and mot toxins it's even earned
the prestigious NSF certified for sport
third-party testing approval stamp now
most people in the performance space
talk a lot about macronutrients like
protein carbohydrates and fats and these
are obviously critically important but
so are the micronutrients like vitamins
and minerals and even if you're eating a
healthy diet it's often hard to get
enough of these vitamins and minerals
along with the probiotics prebiotics and
adaptogens to keep your body performing
at its best it's for these reasons and
many others that I personally take ag1
almost every day now it's of course not
a replacement for eating whole healthy
foods but it is a great way to make sure
that you're plugging in any gaps in your
nutrition to improve your energy bolster
your immune system and just generally
help promote a healthy gut microbiome
and more if you'd like to try ag1 you
can go to drink a1.com perform to
receive five free travel packs plus a
year supply of vitamin D3 plus K2 again
that's drink a1.com perform to receive
five free travel packs plus a year
supply of vitamin D3 plus K2 so our
fourth and final category is that
resting metabolic rate and this is where
we've got the most juice in fact there's
eight very specific items I'm going to
cover here but I wanted to caveat all of
it by making sure we remember here that
change these things change by the hour
so there's a lot of things you can do to
alter resting metabolic rate basil
metabolic rate I can't cover them all
but I pulled out a very specific ones
that I thought you would be most
interested in they have the most
research behind them that's the easiest
to integrate and they are the least
Kookie is how I'll say it the other
final caveat here is remember just
because we acutely change your resting
metabolic rate that doesn't necessarily
mean we're going to lose body fat in the
long term we'll Circle back to that
later but the first of our eight is what
are called spicy foods people this is in
the lore people talk about it a lot it's
it's out there a bunch is it really
real yes technically it's true although
if you wanted to consider this to be a
myth I wouldn't push back that hard this
is how the field honestly Works in a lot
of the cases it's officially there but
is it practically relevant I'll just
share with you the data and I'll let you
decide now I'll tell you my personal
bias I love spicy foods I put hot sauce
or some sort of spice on basically
everything I eat I love it uh I actually
did I grew up not eating anything spicy
probably even into my mid 20s black
pepper was too spicy for me I my family
just growing up never did anything like
that but I learned to love spicy food
when I started dieting I started cutting
weight and losing weight for
competitions and Combat Sports and
weightlifting and things like that part
of that I'd never done it and I'm
bringing this up now because I realized
man spicy food really helped me in that
caloric Management number one when
things are really spicy
I at least personally tend to not eat as
much so I'm not going to Gorge as much
because I'm dealing with sort of a
little bit of the pain and suffering I'm
more likely to stop a little bit early I
don't know if that's really well
documented scientifically but it's
certainly personally true for me
additionally spices herbs
flavors can help you make food not taste
as Bland when you're really controlling
stuff so often times when you're
managing calories you're probably not
putting on
uh flavor fact you're you're managing
fat so you don't have the cheeses and
the sauces and so because of that food
can start to taste a little bit Bland
the beauty of
spices and hot sauces is they can be a
caloric and so you can make food taste
different and you can change it up and
have more variety when your total actual
food intake is not that different day by
day so from a practical perspective the
work we've done with people that are
trying to lose weight and me personally
I love spicy foods I Ed them at ton
here just think about exchanging out hot
sauce or Tobasco for ketchup right easy
win there ketchup has reasonable amount
of calories you can get tons of
different hot sauces that don't have any
and there you go you've saved that 50
calories or 100 calories per serving
which adds up a ton so from a practical
perspective I like it if you don't
that's cool too does it do anything
scientifically yes it actually does if
you eat spicy food and most of the
research here has been done on things
like Chili Peppers ginger red peppers
and even turmeric these will increase
your resting metabolic rate they'll
increase your thermal effective food and
they'll actually oftentimes lower energy
intake like I mentioned earlier we've
seen that routinely there's actually
been research on other spicy foods that
wasn't as promising uh I know that
things people have looked at mustard
horseradish black Peppers those don't
seem to do anything
but the other ones I mentioned a second
ago do seem to do that and they're
they're effectively working by giving
you a shot of adrenaline so more
specifically they're increasing and
activating bet beta adrenergic responses
that's the long way of saying adrenaline
or epinephrine and getting sympathetic
Drive you'll see this like pretty
routinely and you don't have to stretch
your imagination too far to think yeah I
eat something super spicy and you get a
little shot of adrenaline all right now
at the same
time this this is a classic Lane Norton
right he Dr Norton a friend of mine
always talks about people majoring in
the minors and this is a good example of
that so technically does it increase
metabolic rate yes does it do it to a
level that you really
care not really sure what you're
functionally talking about here is
probably three to five calories so
officially it does doesn't matter I
don't know um you have you would have to
eat a enormous amount
of red bell peppers you would have to
probably eat ounces or pounds of Ginger
or turmeric for this to have a real
practical output on you so
Additionally you get sensitized or
desensitized to these things so you may
not have the same response over time I
certainly know if you would have given
me Tobasco 20 years ago I would have had
a much bigger adrenaline response than I
do now and so since we know that's the
mechanism is it then still leading to
additional increases in my resting
metabolic rate I actually don't think it
does I would assume me personally
probably nothing because I'm I'm I'm so
used to it by now so when you balance
the like technically officially I could
pull up a a systematic review or a paper
and show that it increases metabolic
rate if someone doesn't like it or it's
not a preference or they're traveling
like should you really be going out of
your way to strongly encourage spicy
foods for people to boost metabol
ISM I don't think so right probably not
the biggest win so while I technically
have this on our
list again if you said this is on your
list of things that don't work I
wouldn't push back that much either
moving on then the second on our list is
actually surprising enough water intake
there is more than a small amount of
research on water increasing metabolic
activity if you think about this for a
couple of seconds it makes perfect sense
I actually know one paper specifically
looked at I think like 16 or 17 ounces
of water and found that it increased
resting metabolic rate by 10 to 30% for
about an hour now practically I wouldn't
recommend chugging water all day optim
hydrate but think about what it does if
you're ingesting something at a
temperature that is lower than the
temperature inside your stomach by
putting that in there you'll have to
burn calories to heat that water up in
fact that is actually by the way the
strict definition of a calorie it's the
exact amount of energy it takes to raise
I think it's one gram of water one
degree something like it's pretty close
like the definition of a calorie is how
much energy it takes to increase the
temperature of water so by definition if
your body is working to increase the
temperature of your water then it is
going to be burning some calories now
there's also some and I wouldn't call
this extensive but some research on then
by extension of logic colder water might
be of more benefit than room temperature
water it should theoretically take more
energy to heat up okay but probably the
bigger benefit here if there is one at
all is satiety so I know of again
another study off the top of my head
here that in overweight individuals and
that gave them um I think something like
a half a liter of water which is a
reasonable amount to drink 30 minutes
before meal and those that group
eventually lost more weight so what
you're probably at here is a lot of
people I I've heard in the vernacular
say things like oh a lot of times when
you think you're hungry you're just
thirsty I don't know if that's
necessarily true or not but having dealt
with a lot of folks who have to lose
weight over time again athletes and
regular people I will say in my personal
coaching experience making sure you are
drinking water will help you reduce
calorie intake the amount of food you
eat in a meal and so forth with really
no consequences to digestibility unless
you're you know going extreme with it so
water is another potential option you
can turn to the effect will be
minimal but you start stacking some
things on top of each other and you need
to drink water anyway so not something I
would say to overdo but just making sure
you're not under hydrated is probably
the biggest win here a similar concept
here but probably more effective is
using a different form of temperature
regulation that is the temperature in
the environment you're in so there have
been several studies that have looked at
lowering the thermostat in your house by
even a few degrees and that can lead to
substantial and significant loss of body
fat over time same exact concept here if
your body has to work a little bit
harder to keep itself at a certain
temperature that is caloric expenditure
you've boosted your metabolism and it
will result in a practical and
meaningful loss of body fat now I
wouldn't necessarily Advocate dropping
the thermostat so much that you're fre
freeing and your fingers are frozen you
can't type and work but maybe a notch or
two I have friends that have done this a
lot over the years where they bring it
down one degree for three months bring
it down another degree bring it down
another degree and just slowly work
themselves down 3 or four degrees where
they used to keep their house at 72
degrees and now they keep it at 66 or
something reasonable like that if this
feels like majoring in the minors to you
fine again my position here was just to
share with you
all the data that we know of let you
know how much it works how well it works
and then you can decide what to deploy
what to disregard or not based on your
situation and circumstances all right so
playing with temperature whether it is
colder water or colder
environment is another option and
probably more effective than the spicy
food thing but still we haven't I
probably haven't sold you a ton on
things that are really going to move the
needle but we're going to change that
here soon fourth on our list is
something I've talked about now and that
is caffeine there is a lot of data on
this I will summarize the entire field
but you can generally expect something
between like a 3 to 11% increase in
resting metabolic rate that's going to
last somewhere between an hour to three
hours this is very very well
documented pretty easy it's a stimulant
it's going to rev up energy it's going
to tell your body to expect energy
output so it's going to get you going
nicotine is next on my list and it has a
very similar effect the magnitude of
effect is a little bit smaller generally
more like 5 to 6% increase and resting
metabolic rate and it's going to last
for the same you know 60 Minutes 120
Minutes something like that now I
personally don't use nicotine we've used
it and some clients they've asked for it
and we've done it with some success
there I personally like to avoid it as
much as I can but those data are there
and and use it how you
will similar and now we're up to number
six on the list is green tea or green
tea extract you'll see this abbreviate a
lot of
GTE has similar effect of caffeine but
in the four to 5% range for about the
same length and duration as we've
mentioned for some of the stuff prior
with water and spicy foods one thing
that has been documented pretty
consistently with caffeine nicotine and
green te is they all also affect satiety
so they're appetite suppressant so is
the benefit really in the elevation and
resting metabolic rate I don't know
maybe yes maybe no but if it helps you
just not feel as hungry and not then
overeat that's probably the real win but
options nonetheless a lot of people are
already consuming these things I don't
think you need to go in there and add
additional stimulus to your life if
you're already on them you don't have to
use these at all but one more time they
are options to use or not at your
discretion number seven on our list is a
combo I had to do it this way if not the
list would have been 50 things or more
and I'm generally going to call these
Thermo Regulators so this is a handful
of herbs and drugs and other stimulant
like factors that are going to have a
similar impact as caffeine and green tea
and so on and so forth but they're
not in those forms just to give you a
couple of examples wonderful scientist
Bill Campbell friend of mine in Florida
has done some work in the past on Guana
uh you can Google that one up there g u
a r a n a um combined with other
elements much of the research in this
field and the reason I'm calling them
you know Thermo Regulators is because
they're rarely single ingredient things
so they're multiple herbs combined with
multiple different things and
combinations and Cocktails and so you
don't know what the individual effect is
but nonetheless in these
multi-ingredient Thermo
Regulators in in Bill study in
particular I I think they gave their I
think in young healthy men probably the
college kids that are running around his
lab and they saw about a 10% increase in
resting metabolic rate for about three
hours post exercise now what I liked
about Bill study in particular of course
because he's such an awesome scientist
is they had a placebo group and they
reported the placebo group what I mean
by that is the placebo group had a 3%
increase in resting metabolic rate so if
you actually kind of cancel that out you
could still see about a 7% bump in RMR
here
which I think their data was something
like it took them from about a group
average of 8 or
1,850 calories to 2,000 So 150k Cal bump
from this Guana based multi-ingredient
supplements tons of other Studies have
been done like this one in particular I
know actually several of them have used
things like
caffeine plus GTE plus herbl and stuff
like that and if you go back to the
number numbers I just gave you on green
tea and caffeine combine them with other
ingredients you'll see about a 10% total
increase again going to last two to
three hours others have been done on
caffeine GTE and nasin combined with
actually uh something called Garcinia
Cambogia which was the original primary
ingredient in hydroxy cut you've
probably seen hydroxy cuts and
commercials all over the place I think
there was actually a bunch of problems
with people with getting liver failure
so they took this ingredient out of it U
so it's no longer in there to my
understanding but it was in the original
formulation but nonetheless you throw
all those things together and you might
see a 15% or greater increase in
RMR last one here similar caffeine plus
GTE plus yiman another one showed about
a 15% bump so you can basically see here
kind of no matter what combination you
have of these stimulants and herbs about
the higher end of the impact is a 15 or
so% increase for about 2 to 3 hours
right whether that fits in what you like
and and how you live your life that's up
to you I personally don't use any of
these for fat loss clients it's not how
we approach it but if you want to
there's the data make your choice number
eight on my list is getting good sleep
now you don't have to be perfect here
but one of the things we know happens
with really bad sleep even on a single
day is people people tend to seek out
more total calories and it makes sense
you're tired you feel like you're in a
low energy State you're going to want to
get more energy that's exactly what your
body is doing and it is a natural
response this has been shown extensively
in the literature under acute fatigue
from lack of sleep people will search
out more total calories and they'll also
search out food items that tend to be
higher energy density you can think
about these as junk Foods if you'd like
I know personally I search after
carbohydrates I don't know why but I
really want more bread I really not that
that bread is bad for you but I really
want carbohydrates when I'm fatigued
again intuitively it actually makes a
ton of sense this is the primary and
fastest energy source for your body but
that one hits me very directly so I know
that's something I have to watch out for
and it's been shown multiple times most
people are like that and the physiology
makes intuitive sense so if you're
wanting to then quote unquote speed up
your metabolism ensuring you're not in a
spot repeatedly where sleep is bad
therefore it's not that your metabolic
rate has changed but you're going to
make worse food choices and so your
total energy intake is higher which
means your intake versus energy out that
balance is off which is then going to
lead to eventual body composition
changes so there's more to say on that
but that's if you're a little bit
confused on why that is on my list it's
not necessarily that sleep will enhance
hands your metabolism but bad sleep can
have a number of negative impacts and
one of them being behavioral changes
specifically with food and calorie
intake one thing that will suppress
acutely and chronically as we'll talk
about later your total daily energy
expenditure and specifically RMR is
really bad sleep neat specifically will
go down in the presence of poor sleep
acute and chronic the one night of bad
sleep is probably not a big deal but
magnified over time will make a huge
impact so your neat is going to go down
your drive for Worse food choices and
more food overall will increase energy
expenditure might also go down you know
it's harder to work out you're not going
to take the walks you're not you're more
likely to skip your training sessions or
condense them or just get through it
when you've had a bad night of sleep and
you also are going to potentially see
red reductions in resting metabolic rate
and so for me personally what I do when
I have a bad night of sleep and it
happens I have kids and I travel and
all kinds of things happen three things
I do to mitigate this damage number one
what I've already talked about I will
double triple down as much as I can on
protein basically I'm trying to crowd
out other Foods so when I know I just
really want to go for Burgers and Fries
and stuff like that and I know it's
because I slept for three hours the
night before I'm going to smash a double
scoop of protein I'm just going to keep
it really really really high I still
might go get those foods but I just
don't have the physical space in my
stomach anymore I get full of course
occasionally I'm a person I'll just go
have the burgers and fries I'm not
neurotic about it but if this stuff
happens somewhat regularly you can't
always fall into that trap at some point
you need to make sure you don't do that
willpower is one way but personally I
just make sure I'm smashing protein
throughout the day to reduce that risk
second thing I do is I make sure I hit
all that lowlevel energy expenditure
stuff so maybe I don't have it in me to
do my interval training or my assault
bike or run my Hills or whatever but
I'll make make sure I walk let's move
around let's get three or four of those
10-minute walks in no matter how tired
and sleepy I am or sick for the most
part you can probably get yourself to
walk those couple hundred calories are
going to add up especially again if this
happens frequently uh sauna is another
good one sauna is not a replacement for
exercise but hey you can a lot of times
convince yourself to take a hot bath or
a sauna and get something out of the day
third thing I do and this is going to
stun people but take a nap go ahead and
actually just sleep you could suffer all
throughout the day making worse choices
and skipping your workout or maybe that
30 60 or 90 minute nap while you're
going to feel like you're not working
that time because you're not if it's
substantially enhances the quality of
the next 10 hours of your day sneaking
in a little bit of nap may change
everything and is a good thing to do
again when you magnify this stuff over
time another thing I wanted to fold in
here before we left we spoke about this
at the beginning but to be really clear
and that is the impact of age on
metabolic speed for a long time we have
said and you'll see this all over the
Internet that it goes down as you age
and it may sum but more recent research
suggests that most of that is being
driven by a lack or loss of muscle mass
so if you preserve the amount of muscle
you have as you age you should not see
that much of a decline in your
metabolism if you look at folks and this
specifically happens
in that early teen to early 20s range
where people say
wow I eat kind of the same and now I've
all of a sudden gained these five or 20
or 40 pounds in the last couple years
and they look back and they think well I
used to play sports and now I don't yeah
these things are all true but the
reality of it is as you get past that
and you start getting into the 20s and
30s and 40s and 50s most of your change
or perceived change in metabolic speed
is a function of losing muscle remember
muscle explains up to
80% of your resting metabolic rate
that's the thing that will really change
it and drive it so that's a nice little
lead in to what we're going to talk
about next which is how do we make sure
we have not only acute but chronic
changes in our metabolism so let's get
into those options right now the acute
changes we just got done discussing are
mostly beneficial
if they can lead to an increase in
either energy expenditure or
neat The Chronic ones are probably going
to be more predictive of long-term fat
loss I used an example earlier and we'll
do it one more time to finish out this
point if you say ingested caffeine and
you looked at your rate of fat oxidation
or fat burning it would go up your
resting metabolic rate would go up but
if you just sat there on the couch for
the next three hours what will happen
likely is not only will it come back
down to Baseline but then it actually
might go below Baseline and that's your
body's way of saying we gave you more
potential energy but you didn't do
anything with it therefore we're going
to balance that back out by lowering
energy and I'm saying that to say while
we discovered eight different ways to
enhance your metabolism
acutely they may not have any impact in
long-term fat loss if you didn't use
them to actually burn more calories you
then need to use the caffeine to give
you more energy to work out harder or
longer and that's been shown extensively
or the green tea extract or the spicy
foods or whatever the case is so you
want to think about acute activators are
ways to give you some motivation if you
will to get you up to make you help you
move more throughout the day to bur more
energy but if you just increase fat
burning and then you don't use the fat
that fat will get stored right back
again and your net result will go
nowhere and so they don't have a broad
last
impact on fat levels I really needed to
make sure that point was clear because
when we now get into these chronic
adaptations that's what will
functionally change your net result with
what you're finally looking for but the
system gets tricky because as I just
alluded to it will adapt and respond so
what works your first week or six weeks
or 6 months may not continue to work and
it can give you a false sense of a slow
metabolism or that calories don't matter
that's not the case but the system
changes so what is going to move it and
then how do I anticipate and prepare for
and adjust based on my body's response
to a changing
Target going through the four different
areas these first ones are very fast
thermal effective food there's nothing
really here I don't know of any way to
chronically increase your thermal
effective food I guess the closest
analogy or thought we could have here
would probably work in the opposite
direction which is to say something like
theoretically and and there's some
reason to think this is the
case chronic changes in your gut
microbiome may actually upregulate or
downregulate enzymatic activity that
makes you more efficient at breaking
down certain macronutrients if you don't
eat much protein or you change the type
of protein you eat and then you
chronically ingest it you will increase
the enzymatic activity needed to break
those things down and so you'll actually
probably get more efficient at breaking
down Protein that's why if you're not
used to say eating a a steak and then
you have one your stomach might feel
really heavy or oh my gosh that's hard
to digest but people that eat it every
day don't feel that same thing I have no
issue at all digesting red meat but I
eat it really constantly if you were to
bring something in your stomach I'm not
used to you get the idea there we have
some issue so the only thing really to
think about thermal effective food
chronically is if anything it might get
lower because you've changed gut
microbiome properties to be more
efficient at breaking that food item
down so instead of burning 20% maybe
it's now down to 15 so I don't know
necessarily the the case here but we'll
certainly say we'll check this off the
list of things that will change
chronically that'll enhance and speed up
my metabolism so we got to go somewhere
else next ones up are then neat and eat
so in terms of neat again we don't
really have much of a chronic effect
here the only thing I could maybe argue
would be if you have made something into
a pattern and a habit so say you go for
those three 10-minute walks a day and
you do it so much that it becomes a
pattern that you stick to it more often
I guess we could call that a chronic
effect that's not really changing your
levels at Baseline because as soon as
you stop walking that number comes right
back down so not really a chronic
benefit we can see there the one thing
we can say here is what we talked about
earlier in that people who have a close
relationship between an increased in
caloric intake and an increase in neat
are the ones who are most likely going
to be described as your fast
metabolizers and ones that don't will be
your slow better than that again we
don't have really a chronic effect on
neat so we struck out on thermal effect
we struck out on neat what about energy
expenditure from exercise or eat yeah
kind of the same boat so
on one hand energy expenditure during
exercise the more fit you are the harder
you can train the more you can do it and
you can recover and and so you should be
burning more
energy but on the other hand the more
fit you are the more efficient you
become you're more efficient in your
mechanics and your
movement entic profiles have changed and
and upregulated and downregulated and
oxygen utilization and capitalization
have improved improved and so your
energy demand per work is
lower all washed together it's pretty
much uh negates itself so we're not
going to get much benefit from that
either which then leaves us to the real
shabam here and that's resting metabolic
ratee this is the one we're after and
the only one that really matters in
terms of me officially saying yes we
have boosted your metabolism in a way
that you care about and will matter got
a handful of ways to do that and the
very first one is sleep we talked about
this with a cute but the impacts of
sleep are far better explained from The
Chronic
side enormous amounts of data here and
much of it is very recent in fact we had
very little understanding of the
metabolic ties between sleep and
Metabolism until the last really 10
years or so now the relationship between
sleep and metabolism is bidirectional we
talked about bad sleep changing
metabolism a second ago but it goes the
opposite direction as well a bunch of
research I could pull up here but a
couple of ones that I've found most
interesting that I wanted to highlight
one study in particular that came out of
the University of Chicago a number of
years ago looked at 10 overweight
individuals and they put them on a
14-day caloric restriction protocol and
one of the times they went through the
protocol they slept 8 and 1 half hours
the other time they went through the
protocol they slept 5 and half hours so
again University controlled calories in
both situations the only variable that
changed was 3 hours of sleep so now
we're not even talking about the impact
of bad nutritional choices this is
simply even if calories are matched what
happens when you sleep more all right
now the Sleep curtailment group the
sleep that the group that slept for five
and a half hours had a reduction in fat
loss by
55% in absolute terms you're talking
about the difference between like 1.4
kilos versus 6 kilos so almost a full
kilogram difference in fat loss that
favored the group who slept more the
same thing basically happened in terms
of muscle mass uh you can't directly
measure it in the study but it's called
fat-free body mass and just think about
it like muscle mass and this was about a
60% difference so absolute terms you're
talking about 1.5 kilos versus 2 2.4
kilos so almost a full kilogram or about
2 pounds of lean muscle difference this
is substantial remember this is 14 days
that's it and all they Chang was sleep
and we see pronounced increases in fat
and reduction in muscle growth with just
this variable change right so what you
can see there is additional stuff that
they looked at actually fat oxidation um
satiety I think as well was in there but
really problematic uh things going on
when you sleep
poorly that relationship uh if I had to
summarize the literature you're going to
see like a 10 to 60% increased
likelihood of obesity with bad sleep so
there's a chronic effect here that is
very very real one more time it's
bidirectional so we see what I'm meaning
there is if you are overweight you're
probably going to have worse sleep but
worse sleep is actually going to cause
overweight so the cause goes both
directions there a really nice paper
came out pretty recently to be up in the
show notes
you can check it out specifically on the
relationship between obesity and sleep
and how it goes both directions you can
see those details and that but another
thing that is that has been identified
in the literature there is the direct
relationship between muscle mass and
sleep and it goes the way that you would
predict not only does more fat often
times equal worse sleep but more muscle
oftentimes equals better sleep so two
independent things happening there not
enough muscle
bad too much fat bad there's a
relationship as well there but they are
separate and we need to acknowledge that
so it's not only important to make sure
we're we're not over fat but that we
have muscle as well this is actually an
area that's getting a lot of scientific
attention right now that people don't
necessarily realize and that is normal
weight
obesity you heard that right normal
weight obesity so people whose total
body weight is not exceptionally high
but their body fat percentage is really
high probably not kindly put but you may
know this more cloy as skinny fat the
more proper term is again normal weight
obesity but this is an area again
scientifically that's getting a lot of
attention right now because of
acknowledgement of things like that it's
not necessarily just about body weight
but the quality of that body weight
matters a ton more research on this
chronic tie between resting metabolic
rate and bad sleep very very famous
study in the field called The Sleep
heart health study um this was
self-reported sleep folks that self
reported less than 5 hours of sleep per
night had and this is going to stun you
here this was associated with a 200
51% increase in their Hazard ratio of
developing type 2 diabetes Now type two
diabetes and obesity are not the same
thing but obviously there's a strong
relationship there what we're seeing
here is just general metabolic
dysfunction with bad sleep similar
things have been done with impaired
insulin signaling specifically in atopos
cells those are your fat cells and folks
who sleep 5 and 1/ half hours versus 8
and 1/2 hours so we're seeing this in a
lot of different forms and fashion in
fact one of the papers and I'm going to
quote it directly here because it's so
powerful uh specifically said that quote
from a clinical standpoint our study
provides additional evidence that
insufficient sleep May contribute to the
development of or exacerbate metabolic
disorders I can tell you in my coaching
experience it is really really hard to
manage body composition and thus
metabolic rate and somebody who is truly
chronically sleeping really poorly it is
tough you got to fix that sleep or at
least improve it before you expect major
changes in body composition one night of
sleep not a big deal bad nights of sleep
though you're probably going to expect a
reduced resting metabolic rate which is
why it's in our chronic section and a
big big big hammer to swing number two
on our list is going to surprise some
people but it's actually fish oil now
this is a really interesting one we know
of the many benefits of fish oil but
many don't realize the metabolic ones
easy study here to highlight what's
going on 24 females and they did this in
I think they were over 60 656 years old
uh if I'm remembering exactly the age
range there and they gave him three
grams per day of EPA and DHA for a total
of 12 weeks now what's cool about this
study is they actually matched it with
olive oil and so calories were equated
for one group again got the olive oil
which is obviously a very healthy food
Choice the other one specifically got
fish oil and so really in smart study
design here because they of course
matched calories they matched fat and
they gave them not really crummy food
items or low quality stuff but too high
quality quity items and so what that
allowed them to do is tease out the
Direct effects of the EPA and
DHA net result here and
remember this is chronic so what
happened not in the the 60 Minutes or 90
minutes or 3 hours post taking the fish
oil what happened at
rest 12 weeks later about a 15% increase
in uh 14 actually I think increase in
resting metabolic rate they saw an
increase in energy expenditure during
exercise by about 10% and the fat
oxidation rate both at rest and exercise
will increased about 19 and
27%
respectively what's probably more
impressive than all that though is they
saw a increase in lean mass by about
4% take a second to digest that by
simply taking three grams per day of
fish oil not a high dose at all you saw
a chronic elevation in resting metabolic
rate that had a functional and practical
outcome of a 4% in lean mass compared to
olive oil now what do you think this
would be compared to of a lower quality
fat
or worst Food choice in general it would
probably be substantially more so to me
this is incredibly impressive and it is
another reason why taking fish oil is
probably a really smart strategy but in
full honesty here and candidly I didn't
know this I hadn't missed this one I was
pretty aware of basically everything we
talked about so far at this point but I
had absolutely no idea that fish oil
would chronically do this at rest over
time so pretty powerful uh pretty low
hanging fruit and a pretty easy win in
my opinion next
up something we've already mentioned
before and that is adding lean muscle
mass now we've been saying this for a
long time and this is something I need
to offer an official correction on I
have misspoke on these words many time
in the past as many people did we would
often tell people that for every pound
of lean muscle you add you burn an extra
30 to 50 calories per day more
realistically that number is
significantly lower probably closer to
six to maybe 10 calories per day so what
I mean by that is muscle is
metabolically active and so just being
alive being on your body costs you
calories to sustain but that calorie
cost is about again 6 to 10 calories um
per pound of muscle so in that example
if you were to add s pounds of muscle
you will probably expect to in increase
your resting metabolic metabolic rate by
about 40 to 60 K Cals per day now is
that a lot is that not a lot I'll let
you decide but just basic math there if
I take that and I say okay that's about
somewhere between 1,200 and 1,00
calories per month which is four to five
six pounds per year pretty
conservatively there again there's your
10 to 15 pounds over that 5 to 10 years
so we know that it burns calories we
know that it expense experi a huge
percentage of the variance of your
resting metabolic rate we know that it's
the primary thing describing the
difference with age it's the primary
thing describing the difference with
male and female and there are many other
studies that I could bring up to show
that but I think we've made this point
and I hope you believe me by now so
let's go ahead and move on and talk
about other things and by other things I
mean the fourth and final thing on our
list and that is
exercise now the question about whether
or not exercise chronically changes your
resting metabolic rate is tenuous we
don't actually have full scientific
agreement here here's where the field
basically
stands we know that it is particularly
good at keeping your resting metabolic
rate high when you're on a low calorie
diet so that alone again I don't know
that it will increase you above Baseline
but we know that when you reduce calorie
intake just like when you increase
calorie intake it raises your metabolic
rate if you chronically
suppress caloric intake you will then
eventually lower your resting molic in
intake it's going to match it so with
that in mind then if you're on a
calorically restricted diet for a long
time and you exercise you will not have
nearly as much of a drop in resting
metabolic rate so it will preserve
current reol resting metabolic rate
rather than increase it which is a
benefit in and of itself there's also
extremely good evidence that when you go
from even moderately active to
completely sedentary that resting
metabolic rate goes way down uh same
thing has actually been shown with high
level athletes specifically endurance
athletes when they drop training so
their normal level of training and they
bring that down a little bit resting
metabolic rate will come down as much as
10% or more and so while we again can't
make an argument that this stuff will
necessarily boost RMR it may stop it
from going down if it does Boost it it's
probably going to go back to the point
from earlier which is because it yielded
an increase in total muscle mass but
we've already covered that point so what
we're trying to tease out right now is
does this have any additional benefits
outside of just giving you more muscle
now you can look at some systematic
reviews and men analyses here but
generally here's what you're going to
find strength training tends to have the
biggest win
here fun going back to the beginning of
our show remember I said it doesn't have
the biggest win in terms of caloric
expenditure but it does have the biggest
win in terms of chronic boosting and
elevation or maintenance of your resting
metabolic rate usual effect size here
effect rather is about 100 K Cals per
day the data are mixed probably could be
mostly entirely explained by muscle but
the number you're going to see is about
100 in terms of the aerobic exercise
side of the equation it's closer to 50
to 60 K Cals per day so it seems to be
substantially lower for a number of
reasons at the same time because of that
lots of studies are going to say that it
has no effect or minimal effect and
you're probably what's happening is that
number is kind of on the borderline of
the ability to reach statistical
significance so some depending on study
design some studies find that it crosses
the threshold and it is a significant
I'll be a small effect and some it's
just not enough to cross that threshold
so minimal effect if any there with
chronic endurance exercise so because of
that the research on mixed methods of
training protocols that incorporate both
strength and endurance it actually lines
up pretty much perfectly the average
increase in RMR there is about 75 K Cals
per day so endurance exercise maybe
gives you 40 50k Cals strength training
maybe 100 you do a combination of both
you're going to meet in the middle uh in
that range
somewhere right
so that's the best you can hope for in
terms of chronic exercise elevating your
resting metabolic rate one more time I'm
billion reasons to exercise but that's
probably not our our biggest win
relative to our sleep or fish oil or
some of the other things we can do our
fifth and final one is short because
we've mentioned it numerous times now
and that is simply eating more your
resting metabolic rate will adjust to
your chronic energy intake it won't do
it that much or relevance on a
day-to-day basis but if you are
repeatedly eating high amounts of
calories your me resting metabolic rate
will adjust up or down so that all being
said I wanted to tie this thing together
and wrap it up by talking about what is
realistically going to happen with some
of these acute and chronic changes and
how do I wrap that into a complete
picture or a program or a protocol that
one might
use you have to keep in mind the fact
that I as I said at the beginning of our
chronic section it's a bit of a moving
Target here here's what I mean as you
lose weight the equation changes thermal
effect of the food tends to go down why
you're eating less
food okay so we lose some calories to
that neat tends to go down there's a
great paper uh Herman poner at Duke it's
probably most famous for this adaptive
thermogenesis or this
conservation idea I know that um Eric
Trexler and Abby Smith Ryan and Lane
Norton published a paper at least a
decade ago now showing and arguing for
the same thing but what's most likely
Happening Here is neat is the first
response so when your body senses the
fact that you're in a low choric State
it's probably going to bring down your
caloric expenditure through neat in the
the coaching realm and the in the weight
cutting realm this is what we call the
shoulder lean so you know somebody's
really low on calories because they
start leaning up against tables they
start sitting down more their elbows get
placed upon uh stands and and desks and
like that and they're doing this
subconsciously but what we how we always
justify this is their body knows they're
in a Lor loric State and so they want
them to sit down a restmor so they're
really lowering that non-spontaneous
activity anyone who's ever dieted uh or
brought calories down for a long amount
of time that was exactly what I'm
talking about here after that if you
were to continue to be in a low chloric
State you're now going to run into
actual reductions and resting metabolic
rate um especially if you've lost
physical sight and especially especially
if you've lost muscle with that so that
can happen over time so you've lost
thermal effective food you've lost knat
you've lost resting metabolic
expenditure and you'll probably will
even go down in your eat if you are
smaller and you're doing something like
running if you have less Mass to move
you burn less calories and so what
happens here is all four of those
factors can come down So eventually you
either have to then reduce your calories
more or or artificially increase your
energy output more to make sure that
your continuing sles away so one of the
reasons that people tend to plateau in
fat loss is because they're not
accounting for these things to go down
along for the ride now I don't want to
leave you on such a confusing note and
so what I'd like to do now is just
quickly summarize exactly what we've
covered today and then give you a couple
of real practical examples of how you
can combine some of these things to have
an effective total daily energy or
resting metabolic rate or boosting
metabolism Pro call that's going to put
you in the best position possible so
where you don't have to suffer some of
these long-term conservation or adaptive
thermogenesis problems so we started off
by talking about a handful of acute
factors in terms of thermal effective
food the basic thing you're doing here
is eating a higher percentage of your
food in the form of protein we then
talked about neat that is just
effectively strategies like standing
desks and walking treadmills that can
help you move more throughout the day
from the energy expenditure perspective
most likely you'll burn more by doing
endurance or aerobic type of activity or
even higher intensity intervals the last
component then for our acute factors was
a resting metabolic rate and we covered
eight specific factors there everything
from spicy food to water or cold water
to cold air or temperature in your room
or work environment to caffeine and
nicotine and green tea and other
thermogenics or Thermo Regulators there
and then we finished by talking about
having great sleep to make sure you
don't put yourself in a bad food Choice
position once we got through all that
stuff and we remember acute effects
don't necessarily chronically change
into long-term adaptations and so what
are the things that are going to really
boost my metabolism over time we didn't
see a lot of opportunity there for in
thermal effect not a lot in energy
expenditure or neat and so really we had
four main components from the resting
metabolic rate perspective and that is
getting great sleep fish oil at 3 grams
per day adding more muscle and then
fourth one on our list was adding more
calories so the higher caloric place we
could be in while maintaining overall
body composition is going to have us
having the highest and fastest
metabolism possible so now that that is
all in our mind I want to give you a
couple of examples of how you can put
this together I picked a caloric intake
and expenditure of 2500 100 calories
just to give us a starting place so
let's say your goal was to reduce
caloric balance by 500 calories that
would equate to about one pound per week
500 multipli by 7 is about 3500 that's
roughly how much uh calories or energy
goes into a pound of fat not exactly how
it works but that's pretty close I
picked these numbers on purpose one
pound per week is a really good number I
use it a lot that's almost always is
what we go after if you have a lot more
weight to lose you can go a little bit
higher if you have less to lose you may
be a little bit lower but it's a really
good starting place for sustainable
long-term and effective weight loss that
will stay off so not a mistake there but
nonetheless I'm going to give you three
different options of how you could get
to that 500 calorie deficit option one
is to Simply add 500 extra calories of
exercise you don't want to change your
nutrition don't want to change anything
else want get a standing desk you just
want to work harder that's fine you can
do that I'll tell you in my opinion
that's that's pretty hard number one you
don't burn nearly as many calories in
your workouts as you think uh try try
try sitting on a a bike with a heart
rate monitor on and and getting to 500
calories if you're big it's a little bit
easier but if you're moderate to small
that's quite a lot of work so it's not
impossible it's an option plenty of
people have done
it but it it can be check tough
especially if you're trying to use more
calories than
500 this is a hard go all right so in
addition you got to be really concerned
about what's going to happen to neat
remember that adaptive thermogenesis if
you burn a bunch of calories during
exercise there's a really good chance
your body will reduce neat that day so
if you burn 500 calories in the seat of
the bike your body might drop your neat
by three or four or even up that 500
calories as a way to conserve your body
weight and so you can win here but a lot
of folks who have gone through this
where they're like man I trained so hard
I was killing myself in the gym and then
my weight didn't move at
all there could have been an issue with
not necessarily measuring your calories
right and so on and so forth but the
reality of it is at least according to
Dr poner it's possible that your body
was just adapting your neat to match
your eat so your body didn't move
anymore so that's one option it wouldn't
be my top choice though because of those
reasons another option would be the
opposite and that's you cut all 500
calories from your food
candidly this is much easier I've done
this a lot it's possible um sometimes
it's unsustainable some people have a
hard time with hunger and some people
have a hard time regulating food intake
others don't have a hard time so you can
use it it will drop resting metabolic
rate though remember lower calorie
intake means lower RMR and also might
drop neat if you're one of those folks
that have that relationship and you have
a strong tie there you might go down so
you might be chasing your tail a little
bit there if you're doing it in a way
especially if you're not having enough
protein and you're not strength training
this might also long-term result in more
muscle loss which will drop your RMR and
so while again it can be successful I
think it's as limited as the previous
approach and so just getting all your
calories from more workouts possible but
probably not the best approach for most
people getting all your calories by just
eating less again possible but probably
not the most approach if we're using all
the information we learned today we're
going to use some sort of combination
you have four ways to manipulate this
you have thermal effect you have
exercise you have neat and you have a
bunch of ways to alter resting metabolic
rate use any combination I'm going to
give you one sample but please by all
means use whatever fits your preferences
as I've said all day today so just one
example to strike you up here let's say
you needed to burn those 500 calories
and you were able to increase your
energy expenditure from exercise by 200
calories maybe you uh did a little more
on the bike or the whoever knows right
combination of circuits and lifting
weights and whatever but 200 additional
calories sounds really easy trust me
like it's it's harder than you think and
so I think 200 is a pretty reasonable
number especially for for somebody who's
already exercising to do an additional
200 calories per day it's it's a decent
amount more work I actually don't think
much more than that is is that realistic
for many people so 200 calories you're
going to feel that but we got there now
that's how I I got my energy expenditure
from exercise in terms of resting
metabolic rate maybe I'm going to add
that fish oil and that grain tea if you
ran back the numbers I talked about
earlier that might get us an additional
25 or so calories so not a huge effect
there
but we're stacking things on top of each
other taking some fish oil and having a
cup of green tea per day is is not a
super hard thing to get a lot of people
to do so we're going to stack some winds
here then for thermal effective food I'm
going to switch out 15 grams of fat out
of my diet which is about 135 calories
for 30 grams of protein maybe I just
take a David bar there we go maybe you
got a couple of sticks of Maui Nei or
protein powder whatever you want to do
right now that alone did a couple of
things those 30 grams of protein are
about 120 calories those 15 gram of fat
is about 135 calories so that alone we
bought 15 calories but more importantly
we're taking advantage of thermal
effective food so we Dro that
15 we're preserving lean muscle mass
more we've added to satiety maybe then
we'll not have a harder time diet will
be easier maybe we'll reduce calorie
intake but in addition to that we got
another 30 or so calories from that 10%
thermal effect from those 120 calories
from our protein intake so net together
the 15 from low calories plus the 30
from the thermal effect got us another
45 free calories now I know you're maybe
hearing these things you're like oh my
God he's talking about 20 calories and
40 but like in my experience to be
honest with you this is how you make
chloric restriction feel easier no one
that's going through this feels like
they're on a crazy diet worked out a
little bit 15 gram of fat out 30 gram of
protein in I feel full I'm not feeling
like I'm starving all the time or I'm
super restricted I'm not also on a crazy
you know all protein diet or anything
like that you're talking about a pretty
small change that's going to add up
effect okay another change you would
make here maybe you do drop your your
calories one way or the other uh in this
example I just said okay let's cut
carbohydrates by 20 total G
that's 80 calories so we did a little
bit of caloric restriction we did a
little bit of switching out
macronutrients with a thermal effect we
stack all that on top of a little bit of
neat which is a 15minute walk at lunch
gives us another 100 or so calories so
you add all that stuff together a couple
hundred calories from exercise 25 maybe
50 calories from fish oil and green tea
another 50 calories or throw or so by
switching out our macronutrients another
100 calories or so by cutting out a
little bit of energy from this is a
carbohydrate and then and then a walk
per day all that together is going to
get you your 500 calories you're going
to do that in a way that doesn't make
you feel super hungry it won't smash
your neat it won't smash your resting
metabolic rate you won't learn lose
muscle over it and you won't have as
many issues with that adaptive
thermogenesis which means you'll be able
to hold all that weight off a lot longer
than in other approaches I know we
covered a lot of ground today and I
apologize about all the acronyms and the
TS and the Rems and things like that I
know we got a little bit technical with
our math but I wanted you to have some
actual direct practical numbers one of
the reasons I believe we have so much
confusion in this area of metabolism and
boosting your metabolism is because
there's too many generalities thr out
there lack of specificity with
terminology and so people have got
confused and I hope this provided you
some clarity I hope it was actionable
for you in your own individual practice
your coaching practice or just simply
sharing with a friend who's interested
in this field in reality you have a lot
of ways that you can work on your
metabolism while I have to break some
hearts and let you know you can't speed
up your metabolism and there's really no
such thing as a fast or slow
one in practicality you can have that
net result that you're actually looking
for with subtle changes in your total
daily energy expenditure what makes it
feel like your metabolism is found F so
all that to say if you implement any of
these things I would love to know about
it I would love to hear about it whether
it worked or didn't and if you did work
for you and you had success with it I
give you full permission to go around
telling the world that Dr Galpin said
I've officially sped up and boosted my
metabolism and I will not tell the world
any different thank you for joining for
today's episode my goal as always is to
share exciting scientific insights that
help you perform at your best if the
show resonates with you and you want to
help ensure this information remains
free and accessible to anyone in the
world there are a few ways that you can
support first you can subscribe to the
show on YouTube Spotify and apple and on
Apple and Spotify you can leave us up to
a five-star review subscribing and
leaving a review really does help us a
lot also please check out our sponsors
the show would not exist without them
and they're exceptional products and
services finally you can share today's
episode with a friend who you think
would enjoy it if you have any content
questions or suggestions please put
those in the comment section on YouTube
I really do try my best to read them all
and to see what you have to say I use my
Instagram and X profiles also
exclusively for scientific communication
so those are great places to follow
along for more learning my handle is Dr
Andy Galpin on both platforms we also
have an email newsletter that distills
all of our episodes in the most
actionable takeaways we have newsletters
on how to improve Fitness in V2 Max how
to build muscle and strength and much
more to subscribe to the newsletter just
go to perform podcast.com
and click newsletter it's completely
free and we do not share your email with
anybody thank you for listening and
never forget in the famous words of Bill
Bowerman if you have a body you are an
athlete